all right oh I wanted to show you guys
something you
ready
uh no get well this is uh so when I uh
when I became a gishi my teacher
completely ignored
it
and and I thought he wasn't gonna say
anything and then uh I don't know like a
month later he he said I have a gift for
you and
this is the book that we're
studying uh the L Rim book by
Pabon and uh it's original my teacher's
copy uh and uh Tibetan
cloth and uh the paper in tobat was made
from uh a bush which I'm sure cat can
grow
here
uh and it's
it's a little toxic and bugs don't like
it and so it's a you know it's the
preferred paper inbet they don't have
other kinds of paper and uh so it's rare
now
and and then this book looks even older
because my air conditioner leaked on
it and it kind of gave it an antique
look uh so uh
I to me it's very precious it has his
notes what do you call it highlighter
yellow loud
highlighter if I put that on a scripture
he would yell at me but he put it on his
own scripture I guess it's
okay uh so I thought to pass it around
this is the book we're
reading uh we're going to we on the last
part uh this this time and I think we
can finish in Koto if we're lucky but
gisha is kind of slow he keeps telling
stories and stuff so uh anyway I thought
you might like
to to hold it and look at it you're
welcome to look at it you're not welcome
to mix the pages up because it takes a
long time to put it back together The
Backs don't have any page
numbers so please don't mess it up okay
all right Rob's gonna you can hand it
around you can play with it okay it's
okay if you mess it up I don't care I
can I can figure it out okay all
right I think it's the most valuable
thing uh he had and he gave it to me so
it's cool all
[Music]
right okay you guys ready date our ch
334 B yeah good nice okay he says uh de
arum means and by the way today I'm
gonna T you for
$50 somebody said it before
that so 25
each horse race horse race means the the
teachers in a in has to go somewhere or
he has needs to go to the bathroom he's
talking
fast I I did go to the bathroom I just
have to go somewhere so uh
that uh that's a tricky thing it says if
you if you do it like
that and
uh you have to read it carefully what he
just talked about was uh don't expect
people to thank you if you're going to
follow loong if you're going to be a
Buddhist if you really want to be a
Buddhist then uh just help people and
don't worry about if they notice or if
they thank you okay that's Buddhism okay
and and by the way uh in the
beginning people will not thank you and
then if you just shut up and keep
helping people they will start thanking
you all the time they'll stand outside
your car with roses and stuff like that
so it just takes a while for the karma
to ripen all right
so don't expect thanks but by the way
you will get a lot of thanks later okay
uh after the trolls get done with you
people will thank you okay all
right
so CH but so you can read it that way
but I'll take the data CH as more
general which means
um we just finished laa say
laa laa was a short little advises that
came at the end of the seven part loong
so we've been going so
slow through the loong through the text
for developing a good heart uh so that's
a separate book that he put inside this
book okay and It Was
Written I don't know you can say it was
written about a thousand years before
him and uh so he he's been teaching us
loong to get us ready for the six
Perfections because you have to have
bodh cha before you study the six
Perfections okay which just means uh the
reason you're in this
class is to help everybody in the
universe okay and the scale of things or
the scope of things is that big okay uh
it's not even to help people on this
planet this is just one little planet
you know by the way this is a
Planet okay we're at the back of the
planet
class uh but I'm not going to rag on you
okay uh deara means uh if you follow so
I would read it as lovej if you follow
the whole lojo
that I just taught you
okay even though we are living in the
worst of times it means in in
history supposedly these are supposed to
be bad days bad times maybe just before
the end of the world something like that
uh don't worry it's not going to happen
in your time but uh it's uh supposed to
be that these are hard days on this
planet
okay if you
study the worse things get the more
stuff you have to practice with so every
time things get worse and worse uh a
bodh sappa is kind of more happy because
there's more stuff to work with it's
like bodh saa's job is to work with crap
can I say excuse me my wife's not coming
this time so uh your job bodh office job
is to work with the hard stuff the
poison stuff and uh so we're in Lucky
days now we're in Lucky times because
times are bad in the world Denny in
traditional Buddhism it's called nma
sayma Nick means
uh when you make tea with tea leaves
and then there's junk on the bottom of
the cup when you finish that's called
nigma okay uh or there's a pond of water
and the the dirty water is at the bottom
so we're supposedly at the bottom of the
dirty
Pond and there's called five kinds of
dirty there's five kinds of dirty going
on right now okay here's the five I I
took them when you see something in uh
red
letters it means I searched it in John
br's database and I pulled it out for
you okay uh
so there are five okay number one sayma
means uh life times are short it used to
be that people live for thousands of
years and we are at the bottom of the
barrel we're at the worst times people
live for 50 years 100 years it's
considered um bad
times uh first the lifetimes are short
secondly nigma uh people's minds are
more messed up than they were 100 years
ago or a thousand years ago
Umma uh people are angry people are
violent
nma uh These are times when there's a
lot of uh conflict
and then means These are times when
nobody's interested in Buddhism much
okay and uh you know it's just you try
to tell somebody about bod CH or loong
and they're like you know did you see
the football game yesterday and you're
like you know I mean you want to tell
somebody they're G to die and and
they're like you know yeah but you know
I read this thing on my phone it was so
interesting you know people are just not
interested so uh these are bad times
when you're in the bodh SAA business bad
times are good times it's like being an
umbrella seller
during the rainy season everyone else is
unhappy and you're like really happy the
more rain there is the more umbrellas
you can sell okay so these are good days
for Buddy office okay The More Mess up
the world is the better it is for bodh
office and rock stars Ben
okay he's here I'm so happy I I wanted
to play music so
bad this uh Lo that I've been teaching
you guys says p
it came down to seringa say
seringa uh Serling means as I mentioned
golden Island and that's an old word for
Indonesia or uh Sumatra so uh the
teacher the the big teacher from sumo
who taught artia was called a golden
Island teacher sua
Guru uh so this these instructions came
down from him
um and uh after
chawa he he released them to the public
right they were
secret and then about 8 900 years ago
chawa released them to the public and
then he said these
advises about being a bodh Safa in the
bad days make me so happy that if I died
today I wouldn't have any regrets Okay
so so Shang means even if I die Mig
means I I wouldn't have any regrets I
got what I wanted in this life I got the
loj if I die today I'm happy
okay
uh there's a big question
about you know the L J's emphasis is Bod
so the L
J's uh parent emphasis is love or care
for other people and then um then the
the gash type of people they're
curious what was the emptiness
understanding of the loong writers the
people who taught loong how much did
they understand about emptiness and and
there are very interesting uh really
interesting uh discussions about it and
uh like for example dharmar rakita who
taught uh sis loong to Lord AA he was
Abid Dharma he was lowest school and
then he had that experience of cutting
off part of his leg to help somebody who
was sick and then he changed to mind
only and uh
Suba Guru the other one of the other
teachers of AA in Indonesia he was mine
only uh but he switched to middleway he
he went his emptiness Viewpoint went up
to middleway aesa taught uh
middleway aesa wrote the first great LM
in Tibet uh it's about 400 pages in
English translation uh so there's a
question uh how much emptiness do you
have to understand to practice loo okay
what's the you know where should your
emptiness understanding be and soapa has
an interesting uh discussion that's not
in here but um he says uh when people
asked
aesa who followed the
middleway uh who has who which teacher
had been uh most kind to him uh he said
dharak uh who had mind on this who was
mind on this school you know so that's
really weird that the the inventor of L
rim or one of the great people who
started the L
Rim which always teaches middle way uh
by the end of the book we always go
through middle way and he said says my
greatest teacher was my mind only school
teacher and everybody's like why and so
kaapa was disturbed by that and he he's
like
why why would uh Atia say his greatest
teacher was his lower Viewpoint
teacher uh and then
uh soapa says uh it's because he gave
him compassion
and then he says
uh soas says uh if you really understand
life you will understand
aa's
statement and he just leaves it like
that you know you if you really
understand
life you will understand why aesa was
most grateful to the person who taught
him
compassion and even though he he
couldn't explain emptiness in the
highest way you see what I mean it's and
so Capa says there's something important
there you guys figured out so anyway I
think that's so here's where
PAB starts
discussing you know those loon guys
those bodh SAA bodh CH guys what was
their Viewpoint about emptiness and then
he says
is a a very colloquial expression which
means uh if you ask somebody what was
the emptiness understanding of these
loon guys D on man means we can't really
say for sure we can't really say for
sure dun on man okay that was uh the
opinion of a lot of loj commentators
that said look we we read these guys'
works it's not
clear uh where was their emptiness
understanding we're going to do the
eight
verses on
Saturday and it's short it's 48 seconds
to recite
it like that okay
um but it has a full emptiness of
viewpoint in it okay it's complete it's
highest Middle Way by the time you get
to the eighth verse 402s
later uh it's uh number one emptiness
okay it's very cool that's why I wanted
to teach it on the 20th anniversary of
diamond mountain okay y
[Applause]
so there's a Lo called uh the Rays of
the light of the
Sun as far as the presentation of
emptiness in L JS like that um what's
that mean
um highest Middle Way highest middleway
okay consequent
school okay
some good means I want you guys to have
the opinion that the L Jong writers were
all higher middle way and I don't care
what people say okay they were all
higher middle way they understood
emptiness okay and I personally don't
think you can
uh eat the poison as a peacock if you
don't understand emptiness okay if you
think that people are not coming from
you you you won't be able to you'll have
a breakdown if you try to serve a lot of
them okay unless you understand that
people are coming from you I don't think
you can can infinitely serve people I
don't think it's possible okay you will
you will get tired or you you'll break
down okay all right what's the opposite
of
that if you understand the pen really
well uh your capacity for service is
unlimited okay uh uh because you're
really just taking care of yourself and
it's similar to the famous Rich guy's
answer about
ethics
right yeah although I
know no he said uh what's it Buddhist
ethic Buddhist morality what's the
definition of right and
wrong yeah if it hurts you
it's wrong if it doesn't hurt you if it
helps you it's right and then you're
like no morality should be how how do
you treat other people and they say no
real morality is to treat other people
well because you know that you are
treating yourself well if you do okay
which means you understand that other
people are coming from from you they are
you if until you understand that other
people are you you cannot truly be
moral
okay
okay which means if you want to practice
Lo Jong well you got to be what what's
cool higher middleway you have to have
a a complete understanding of emptiness
a complete understanding of emptiness
means a complete understanding of
dependent
origination which means everyone's
coming from me
okay and there's nobody who's not coming
from me is emptiness got it so it's not
so complicated and it's not so
philosophical it just means everyone's
coming from you depend on origination
cause and effect
Engle and then there's nobody who
doesn't come from you is emptiness and
that's all that's all you need to know
and that's highest middle way okay you
can't really be
compassionate until you understand
that there's no difference between other
people and you and what you do to other
people you are doing to yourself okay
then then you can be compassionate then
you can have real compassion okay which
is really
self-interest it's just a bigger me like
you thought you had weight problems
before now you're equal to the weight of
all
people anyway okay we talk about
[Music]
carbohydrates they me now there's a
tradition in uh oral teachings in
Buddhism uh at the beginning of of a new
day or a beginning of a new session
especially K here it's called k k means
uh repeat
everything uh do a review of what you
talk taught the day before and uh it
slows down an oral teaching that's kind
of what happened to our oral teaching
for the last 14 years if you have to
review everything because not everybody
comes every
time uh it slows things down but there's
a tradition in Buddhism that you should
review something at least three times
after you get the teaching okay so in a
in a new country or a Western Country
it's good to review things in when you
start the
class uh and he says but when you're on
the lower topics before you reach the
bodh sappa topics I give you permission
not to review you know it's better to
get through the bodh sappa stuff before
you die okay so if you don't you know
review the lower things like death
meditation things like that he says it's
okay with me because I just want to make
sure you get to the bodh St when you get
to the bodh St I expect you to repeat
and review okay but he's kind of giving
us permission not to you know go over
and over the lower points by the way we
will have a grand review of this entire
14-year teaching
uh we're going
to I'll teach you uh emptiness from the
greatest book on emptiness which will
take about nine years I started this
morning again I'm halfway done with it
uh but
uh but uh I
thought we should review what we did for
the 14 years but without spending much
time so me and Tim have a plan to uh
I'll do a hundred uh I'll teach you a
100 meditations from this Lum room okay
half hour meditations so we'll I'll
teach you a hundred different
meditations that you can do for this
book for the last 14 years uh I'll start
teaching you half hour meditations and
the first one Tim will
be what
day Friday or Saturday okay we'll start
on Friday or Saturday and we'll go for
it'll take a year or something and I'll
teach you a 100 different
meditations uh on on the
Lum and uh and then we'll record them
and uh you can have them on your
app Tim's going to figure out how to
make the
app and giving the cause and effect
relationship of fundraising with app
he's going to work on that not me I no
I'll do a little bit uh so anyway we'll
do a 100 meditations and you can for the
rest of your life you can have some fun
you know ask your phone AI to give you
an a random meditation from the alarm
room and and it'll give you okay we're
working on that okay um
so we won't repeat the teaching now good
news yeah somebody uh went into town
yesterday cat which town
Buie Dinara Dinara and cat went into
[Music]
town these are the guys that shoot the
rattles stick so
uh anyway they went to a columb Clan
member's house by the way they are nice
guys and they did make our roads for
example so they must be nice guys but um
anyway uh there's a peacock hanging out
there and I guess it was just a
coincidence oh two peacocks okay that's
a good one that's like the best ones I
ever saw uh in
buy that's that's something
that must have freaked you out I don't
know you should have brought it over
here okay maybe we can borrow
him uh so there's uh teaching the whole
teaching of this book that's that yellow
book that's going around that's
uh it's 24 days the original teaching
was 24 days uh my teacher was there at
one of those
uh extended teachings he was the corer
uh which mean neara he was the
refreshment guy my teacher was the
refreshment guy for like a thousand
participants you know because my teacher
at that time was a bad
boy and his main interest was to spread
thumb packs at the door because the
monst didn't wear
shoes you
understand and that's the kind of thing
he was
doing and uh he he had no hope of being
a
gishi and uh P came over to thank the
refreshment
people uh this happened to me
they they announced that the dama was
coming to our
Temple and uh and everyone was excited
and people asked me are you going to be
the translator and I said no I'm going
to be the Momo
cook I won't even get to hear his talk
and uh and I said Mark you know mark my
words and that's exactly what happened
uh my competitor was chosen as the
translator and I was chosen as the Momo
cook and then uh I made Momos all day I
didn't even get to go to teaching and uh
and he went up to my teacher's
room and like half an hour later he sent
down word he saysi want to meet the Momo
cook personally you know and I'm
like he said these are the best M I ever
had I'm
like you know and
so so I got to go up and meet them all
in person all these Fat Cats PMA yeah so
anyway H why am I talking about that uh
I don't
remember oh yeah so Kenra was um was
doing the refreshments and
PAB uh insisted to come and meet the
refreshment the young refreshment guys
and he came up to my teacher and he
grabbed him by the
head and he said you're going to be a
good one this is a good one you know you
know and he he
went and then uh after that my teacher
uh beat 15,000 gishes he was number one
out of 15,000
mons
okay so whoever is doing the
refreshments uh so anyway
um there was 24 days of teaching and we
have finished now 23
okay after 14 years we finished 23 days
and right now we're going to start the
24th day uh the last day okay so here we
go uh this is not the last last day of
the teaching because I taught you the
last days first so you could meditate on
the other days so I taught meditation
first um but this is the last day that
we will do and here we go it's kind of
exciting to me I think we'll do half
here if Gesa can get to the
subject and we'll finish the other half
in Kyoto in December okay so try to come
Kyo is unusual because uh it was
transplanted from China of the tongue
Dynasty like 1,400 years ago the the
peak of Buddhism in the greatest Empire
in
history uh at that moment it was planted
transplanted to
Japan and then it died in China and uh
so really the the last great
classical Buddhist city in the world is
Koto uh and uh it's a nice it's a nice
place to finish the L if you have a
chance then come okay it'll be limited
how many people can come is limited
okay it's also a small City how many
people a million or something less I
don't know it's a it's hard to find a
big room I think Tim got the biggest
room there he fought he fought for it we
got it but still it's limited okay all
right uh means now we begin the 20th
dayup means uh I will teach something
from the briefer
presentation of the jewel of all good
qualities and this is a nickname for the
short
B okay the shorter version this is a
nickname for it okay he's gonna
quote the
Buddha
Shen uh all of the buddh of the the past
and the future and who are around
nowadays they all traveled only one path
and that was the path of the six
Perfections okay so this is a big big
moment in our 14 years we're about to
start the six Perfections okay and I
personally I've been waiting for 14
years to to get to the six Perfections
it's kind of
frustrating uh so yay we reached the six
perfection
and I always wanted a good explanation
of them you know you hear about
them but I it be nice to have a really
really good expl this is the best
explanation anywhere is in this book
okay uh J so the Llama pabona quoted
that ancient Perfection of wisdom Sutra
that says all the Buddhists walk the
path of the six
Perfections
uh I don't care if you're
studying open teachings I don't care if
you're studying
Tantra uh if you want to go the way that
all the Buddhists walked
before it's the six Perfections you have
to learn the six
Perfections Jones a they uh and then our
teacher said you're going to get a good
explanation of those
six then he asked us to review our
wro preliminary practices which you guys
Georgia and uh Kong ch
sayong ch ch uh kunlong means your
motivation for being here cha uh means
you have to set it every day when you
get here you have to set it you know and
uh people are dying I keep getting
messages from my brother he's uh he's
watching he's doing a death watch for my
stepmother and uh I get messages every
day and I'm leaving on
Monday uh to take to you know help her
die and um so uh you know fix your
motivation every day people are dying
everywhere you know your parents are
dying your your friends are
dying so uh he says fix your CH means
fix your motivation every day you know
set your
motivation I'm trying to do something to
help this world and really it's just a
world of death you can talk about
politics you can talk about AI you know
you can talk about the Samsung just
passed Apple in cell phone
sales this
morning uh but in the end it's just
everybody dying you know so uh he said
you know fix your
motivation CH Jim then the teacher did a
slight review but not much cuz he said
we got to get to the six
Perfections and he did a little review
of the lojong topics that we have been
studying uh he did a quick review of the
lojo I like the words quick review of
the lojo it means now we're finally
Gonna Leave the loo and go to the six
Perfections okay
uh I have been teaching you guys how to
get body
CH uh then traditionally also with
Master Shanti DEA after you
learn the two types of Buon tuna right
the second one is empty this
understanding okay uh after you learn
those uh you should take your bodh SAA
vows and you should commit to bodh bodh
saa's way of life formally you should
take those vows you should make that
commitment in a in a
ceremony okay so at this point if you
don't have bod V you should take bu s
before you start the six Perfections
okay all
right they'll be offered
tomorrow what
time 10
o'cl okay cool it's a perfect timing
okay we're not really supposed to go to
the six Perfection 8 o' that's too early
to be a bu
St all right we'll make an exception uh
yeah he said some people think you can
get to buddhahood without bodh and
bodh and they throw themselves into chak
say
chak chak is a abbreviation for Chu Chen
and z z Chen uh which is uh
two tantric practices that are
emphasized in other
Traditions uh but that kind of uh
skip uh sometimes they can skip the bodh
sappa teachings they say oh you you
don't need this bodh Safa vs you don't
need Boda you can go straight to
meditating on The Emptiness of your mind
or
something okay got it
seriously no
h okay by the way it's a bad habit it
sticks okay it's a bad habit to think
you should think about nothing because
it you
will understand and then it becomes a
habit and then you know you never wash
the dishes okay that's what happened to
your kids all right not everybody's kids
uh so anyway he says don't even dream
about doing Tandra
or higher philosophy if you don't do
your bodh SOS first he says don't even
think about it if you're not in the
business of taking care of everybody in
the universe then don't think about
studying emptiness it's a waste of time
okay all
right you can do all those High
weird tantric practices empty your mind
and you won't get any closer to Buddhism
Buddha
buddhahood you will not even become a
Buddhist okay you won't even be a
Buddhist okay just thinking of that
trying to think about nothing and
ignoring your body of vows or or
learning the body St Perfections the S
Perfections you won't even be a Buddhist
okay you you can you can go this EX
Tantra things you know but in the end
you won't even be a Buddhist okay
okay means uh make it your heart
practice okay till means your palm of
your hand make it your palm practice the
one that's in your
hand the Buddhas sat around for a
zillion years thinking about what would
be the best way to teach
people and they said there's nothing
better than the six Perfections they so
somebody you know all these Buddhists
sat around for billions of years and
thought could we make it any shorter
than six or and they're like
nope okay go Mas Masa means they didn't
see any any other way cheaper way
there's no shortcut to Buddhism you have
to learn the six Perfections okay uh
[Music]
okay
uh I think I found the only mistake in
this whole
carving I love to find mistakes because
it makes me feel smart and uh as my
students know my translator students but
um
here's like the only mistake I ever saw
in this
carving he calls it number two which
number three but anyway
s let's get on to the six
Perfections uh if you want to go to
India there's no hope to get there if
you don't know where the roads are and
this was a big thing in Tibet
they were Yak herders they didn't have
even an
alphabet you know Buddhist teachers
started coming over the Himalayas into
into Tibet I mean for every successful
one like aesa there was a hundred who
died in the
mountains and um you know they then
people got turned on the the whole
country got turned on it became the most
advanced
spiritual culture in history
and there's
300,000 great books it's it's the
greatest religious movement in history
and it was destroyed in 1959 okay so uh
in in the history of human
beings uh the
Tibetan conversion to Buddhism was the
greatest
religious event in
history uh so anyway uh they a lot of
them wanted to go to India and study
and but it was very very difficult it's
like climbing down from Mount Everest or
something it's extremely
difficult so he said look if someone
doesn't tell you how to get to India you
would be a fool to walk south and and
just try to get there okay therefore you
should study the six Perfections you
should follow the path okay deang
this a famous n verse we say it at the
end of every teaching
traditionally and it means by the karma
of listening to this teaching may I
complete the collection of Merit and the
collection of wisdom okay so there's two
sets of causes you have to finish one
creates a Buddhist body and one creates
the Buddhist mind so you have to there's
two kinds of good karma you have to
collect one creates the Buddhist body
and one creates the Buddhist mind so you
gotta and you have to do both of them at
the same time okay you got to collect
the causes for a body which can travel
to all planets and you have to collect
the causes for a mind which can see all
things okay
yes and the six Perfections combine
those things perfectly okay the six
Perfections
combine all the karmic seeds you need to
get a physical body of a Buddha and a
mental part of a Buddha
[Music]
okay uh the first five
Perfections are the help you create your
physical body of a Buddha and the last
Perfection helps you create uh the mind
of a Buddha there's some discussion
about that ision into one and five and
one I would do it I would do it uh
312 okay personally first three
Perfections body last two Perfections
mind fourth Perfection split that's
traditional which you guys know okay I
don't know why he said it the other way
but must be something
there now he gives the proper number
uh so now I'm going to teach you guys uh
the six
Perfections I'm going to teach you how
to be a bodh Safa and he says bodh SAA
for you to be a bodh Safa you got to
learn the six and the four okay to be a
bodh SATA you got to learn the six and
then you got to learn the four okay
what's the six it's the six Perfections
okay and we'll be going through those
now uh until we finish this book okay uh
and then for the last two Perfections
we'll go deeper for nine years okay uh
so gesla what's the four so technically
there's 10 Perfections okay technically
there's 10 Perfections uh six to become
a Buddha and four uh to attract students
okay to attract disciples there's a so
if you're going to be a bodh Safa and
you learn the six Perfections and you
become
a if you become a person who has some
Enlightenment in you then you are you
are a valuable resource for the whole
world you are extremely valuable even
just sit here for one week you are
extremely valuable in the world you're
like better than than all those tennis
stars and golf stars
and I saw a definition of sports it was
uh was
it the intelligence to learn it well and
the stupidity to think it
[Laughter]
matters I said wow that's pretty
good the intelligence to learn it to
fine details of football and this to ID
to think anyone cares about it or it's
going to help anybody so anyway
uh if you know football well you can get
a job on TV but if you know bod staa
stuff well you can help people okay so
you're just to sit here for one week
you're extremely valuable person okay
and but if you don't know how to pass it
on to other people then the value is
limited okay if you don't know methods
of attracting students and and being a
magnet for students uh then you cannot
help so many people you know and it's
not about uh becoming famous or
something like that it's about helping
people so there are
tricks to attract people in a good way
in a healthy way not that you get more
money or you get more fame or something
like that but but just to wake people up
who are watching the football all day
you know how to wake them up is a
separate topic from the six Perfections
and it's called the four in in DCI we
call it the four Magnets How magnet how
to attract people you know how to how to
okay so you have something valuable but
the whole world doesn't know you have
something valuable how do you let the
World know and you have a moral
responsibility to let people know and to
share once you understand
anything in this
room you have a moral responsibility to
share it get on the plane go to
paruay you know okay you have a you have
a responsibility okay you you would be a
strange person if you didn't care about
other people if you learned something so
precious and you didn't try to share it
with people you would be weird Okay so
there's there's six Perfections and then
there's four ways to share with other
people in a good way not in a what do
you call we don't bang on people's doors
and did you hear the good news you know
take take take that book flap it in
people's
we don't we're not allowed to do that
actually okay all right we used to have
some guys come from one of those groups
to the to our temple in in New Jersey
and we always had good debates uh we
invite them in have coffee and uh we had
debates with them my sisterin-law
sis yeah my wife's sister she had a very
terrible disease and she lost the use of
her arm and
uh so the the Mormon gu
came uh four years ago and they still
come every
week uh to help her you know like two
young
men so you know I have a feeling that's
more buddhis
SAA okay so uh that's a great thing
that's a beautiful thing okay that's
amazing no Buddha has knocked on her
door yet uh to help her so
[Music]
okay doing okay what time I have to shut
up
Tim don't say be careful what you
[Music]
[Applause]
wish
okay uh they do this thing they said
guess I teaching for an hour and then
after an hour I'm like looking at
breakfast you know and they're like oh
did we tell you about the Q&A I'm like
no okay
uh okay here's a picture here's my
favorite picture of myself actually uh
yeah uh I some some magazine was doing
an article about 30 years
ago uh about my jewelry
business and my Buddhism and um at the
time I was learning how to cut diamonds
which was not part of my
job uh but I wanted to know so I I did
it at night I studied at night you know
like from 8 to midnight I learned how to
cut diamonds and um so you can see the
diamond between the fingers that's a
rough
diamond and uh it's very important for
Buddhism okay anyway
Dum so here we go t we're going to start
the six
Perfections Chila LSU I'll say something
about bodh SAA career in general number
one number
two uh I'm going to spend some extra
time on the last two Perfections which
is meditation and yeah understanding
emptiness so our extra time is is going
to be N9 years in emptiness
jail okay all right uh but he does spend
some time on it extra time then he says
D What's
d yeah where's the
picture uh Diamond way okay and and
there's a reason why Diamond way is
called Diamond way okay and that's a
long story uh we'll have to talk about
it but uh
what's cool about L RM is that you get
Diamond W before the end of the L RM and
you do not get that in the gashi course
you know you can spend 25 years in the
monastery you do not get diamond
we uh in L Rim you get diamond way at
the end okay so it's cool whether Lo
Jong has Diamond way or not I'll leave
it up to you to
debate okay
yeah you should debate it we used to
have debate ground out here that's why
we built this uh Place back here it's
kind of all spider Webby
now but uh if you're in the mood you can
go back there and argue you know you
don't have to argue in the kitchen you
can argue out here okay
uh but in in L Rim you do get diamond
Wave by the end you don't get initiation
but you get some teachings on on it okay
uh I guess we'll have to do that uh okay
Tada here's the six Perfections
doubleim there are six Perfections okay
in China they go like this
right uh in America we go
like uh okay jimba is uh I struggled
with uh how to translate jimba I
struggled with how translate all these
words for for 50 years uh but I think
Jima you can say
generosity but I think it's not quite
the right English word giving is a nice
word sometimes I like to say sharing
nowadays sharing what you have I think
that has a good feeling to it you know
share what you get
some cinnamon rolls at Peace Tree Cafe
Mr bin uh share with other people okay
giving suim means ethical Behavior
follow ethical
Behavior
Uh there's an English word morality but
um it for those of us who grew up in
America uh it has a lot of other
meanings that are kind of like you
know so I don't know I think ethics
ethical life something like that uh so
uh you can translate it as
patience I don't know if it's the same
thing as not getting pissed
off okay not getting upset I I like not
getting upset it's a lot harder to not
get upset then not get angry right uh
okay so nowadays I'm kind of feeling
like not get upset with be a good word
syndrome means
effort uh joyful effort to to enjoy
working hard something means meditation
and shub means uh understanding
emptiness basically wisdom those are the
six
Perfections okay we're about to start
this is a big deal it's been 14 years
okay we finally reached the six
Perfections at this moment dumala uh
dumala jimba means uh giving okay
sharing uh then he mentions uh
he's gonna give a
short definition of the first Perfection
l l
get the the essence of the Perfection of
giving is the
intention that's the first thing he says
the essence of the Perfection of giving
the first thing he says is the
intention what uh where you want to to
share what you have with other people
okay that's called that's kind of his
definition of the Perfection of giving
the intention the State of Mind where
you want to share L long get l means uh
share your body okay it means your
time okay body is easy I'd rather cut my
finger off than give you six hours uh
but
okay so body long means the things you
possess and then gam means uh your
virtues your your goodness okay sharing
those things the desire to share those
things is the definition of giving
okay all giving can be divided into
three types number
one
uh say
s sing means material stuff you
know cars food money okay those material
stuff
uh he's not going to give you the other
two kinds of giving yet okay the first
one is physical giving okay and we'll
get to the rest later okay and he says
look
the biggest kind of physical gifts you
can give is your body you can give away
your body okay and people have done it
right
uh
dharmar give away your flesh okay give
away your body and then he says uh where
is it
Rob
Samba somebody gave me a bag of Samba
coming into the class yeah
yeah uh crushed barley some guy sat
there ding ding ding okay uh but anyway
that's
um so every monk has a sampa bag tied to
their
belt and it's a little bag about this
big and you keep a couple of handfuls of
SAA powder and uh you don't have to stop
the gishe activities for food
because this is allpurpose food it has
everything in it you can live on this
for like a year you don't have to eat
vegetables for
example uh so uh all monks have a little
bag of sambba tied to their belt and
they take snacks during the day and they
don't stop the gishi course doesn't stop
to eat you know and uh so anyway he says
give somebody a little pinch of your
Tuma up to give giving your body this is
giving okay s okay uh SAA means uh TMA
means one spoonful of SAA
[Music]
okay Den is uh you guys got the next
picture this is like
uh I don't do you ever do that you sit
around and try to figure out which bills
you can
pay like if I don't pay this one they
shut off the
electricity but the water people they
give you an extra week you know so you
know you're
like juggling with your bills okay so
just keep that in mind juggling your
[Music]
bills uh if you can't learn to share
what you have okay if you cannot learn
to share what you have listen
there have been times in your past birth
when you were
brma or Shakra these are
two deities worldly deities okay and
they are uh these guys use planets as
marbles ding
boom they're so powerful they use
planets they play with with planets like
you
know you know they boom you know they
this so try to
imagine not the person who owns all the
money on this
planet imagine somebody who has a
thousand planets in a bag and plays
marbles with them I mean that's how
power and they they exist people like
that exist he says therefore you and I
we have been brought
and we have been Shakra in our past
lives we have sat on the sun and played
marbles with planets okay forget not
having all the money on the planet you
played with the planets you you you have
been
there but you didn't
share
therefore where's that picture you're
trying to decide whether to pay the
electricity bill or the water bill okay
look man you used to play marbles with
planets now you're sitting there like
should I pay the water bill or should I
pay the electrical bill you know you are
evidence that you didn't do the first
Perfection your life is evidence that
you didn't do the sixth Perfections you
were like them you used to have that
kind of money you know you didn't pay
the electricity bill you invented
electricity you know and then here you
are you know cuz you were cheap and when
you had it you didn't share it and now
look at you you know you're trying to
pay your bills you know he says sad
okay because you didn't giveways because
you did not share with
others number 10 Dan on
K means that's why you're in such a
lousy situation nowadays okay you're
trying to figure out which bill to
pay think about
it so open up your heart and open up
your pocket and give give to people just
keep giving okay and I tell you from 71
years old to all you young
people uh if you Mak it a habit to give
away what you have you will just get
richer and richer and richer the money
will chase your around okay really okay
it's weird it's really weird you know I
try to run away from
money and and I it just and I I I'm what
do you call I'm an real experiment of
this principle I used to sit there with
my electrical bill and try to figure out
about how much I could pay and if you
keep being generous with what you
have uh not with what you don't have by
the way
uh what you have share what you
have as a
habit uh you will be super happy and you
will be super successful uh in your
business for example okay and and it's
just true I can tell you it's true it
takes a while to figure it out but you
figure it out after a while just keep
giving you know don't give more than you
have do not get into debt uh do not
cause your family trouble because you're
such a bony
haa okay but uh give what you can when
you have it and and never stop giving
give something keep giving something and
and you will always have money all the
time you
know yesterday morning I got a yesterday
afternoon I got
a I got a funny uh text on my phone uh I
mean I could show it to you but it says
I I I couldn't get your number right and
I text the person back what number they
said your credit card number and I'm
like in regard to
what and they say uh the refrigerator
were gonna buy with your credit card and
I'm
like which refrigerator and they're like
oh it's it's 2,000 bucks not bad and uh
I'm like and and we think we got your
number wrong and we just need you to
help us get it
right I swear you could I'll show it to
you and I'm like well I didn't know that
I was buying your
refrigerator but uh I'm okay let's do it
and and uh so I sent them the right
number and they bought it
and you know it's just keep doing weird
stuff like that and uh and you'll you'll
have a that was after the dentist uh
wrote me that I had the wrong uh credit
card number for the
$8,000 uh tooth fixing I'm doing for
somebody uh somebody I met so just keep
doing weird stuff like that and uh it
just comes back to you I mean I hate to
say it over and over again but keep
being generous not with what you have
okay not if I didn't have 2,000 I
wouldn't have done it I would have said
look I only have 200 I can give you a
100 you know but if you have it just
don't hesitate and give it and I swear
to God it comes back it just keeps
coming back more and more and more and
more and it's and it's fun it's it's fun
to be uh to try to be a buddist St is
fun okay and just keep trying
okay uh we have some time to do Q&A a
few I like one Q maybe a Q and half an a
how's
that anybody Tim you got that weird
[Music]
box then I erased the message on my
phone because I thought probably
somebody could see it get the real
number
who that I didn't approve of
uh
question okay thank you for answering
questions today I have a question about
trolls
troll let's say you have someone
trolling you and you say thank you for
your troll it's greatly appreciated I'll
put you on hold does ignoring them make
them giving uh make them stop or is it
just the fact that you're not responding
and with more
unkindness yeah that's a good question
so if someone criticizes you online it's
kind of
a uh I've been the object of very heavy
criticism online and it still hurts me
sometimes it hurts me and uh uh I I
don't know I I thought about it a lot
and um it's a new thing you know for
10,000 years we developed in humanity
ways
to talk to each other you know you don't
say this to somebody and you know but we
don't have a system
for civil Behavior online we don't have
it we don't we haven't
probably our children will have rules
you know hopefully about how to behave
online but we don't have it's new it's a
new thing so people can say things about
terrible things about you and you have
no way to prove it's wrong you have no
way to answer it uh you can't defend
yourself uh and people who are semi
famous are are often the victims of it
and even the news uh the big news people
and like that and we found out here we
found out about it and um I don't know
my my
personal approach is to I I think it's
uh I think it's valid to State the facts
somewhere you know and say Here's what
really happened or something like that
put it online
somewhere uh I think that's
okay uh but this kind of uh anger or
what do you call it uh you feel in
invaded or you feel attacked unfairly
that feeling I think that that takes a
lot of management it takes
emotional management to deal with it
successfully and and I you know I I
didn't know about online stuff and I
didn't know about news what happens when
the news really gets interested in you
uh I didn't know about it and um and
it's terrible and but I I don't think uh
I think how you
respond is is the main thing you know
and I think you should respond with
Grace and you should respond with truth
and then I think most importantly you
should let it go cuz uh you
know it just went to 10 million people
so you know I don't think there's much
you can do practically just I I I had a
companies come up you pay us $50,000 we
get it off the internet you know my my
well somebody I know used to do that in
business you just pay you pay a company
and they eras everything and nobody
knows you went bankrupt and uh you can
do that and and I know there's Co I've
I've been approached by companies like
that but I I don't feel like it's the
right thing to do I feel like the reason
it's coming is that you criticized other
people so I think as a bodis SAA or as a
Buddhist you you have to the first
reaction has to be I must have done this
to somebody else uh that's always the
first reaction has to be I must have
done this to somebody else now I'm going
to be really careful that I don't start
rumors or something like that and and I
think that's
the that's the way to handle it and and
I think it's very hard not to feel upset
and it's very hard not to get angry and
and it's uh very hard not to be
frustrated but those are just more bad
seeds so I think as a Buddhist um you
just have to anytime someone hurts you
or criticizes you your first reaction
has to be oh I must have done this to
somebody else so so let me control
myself in the future and that's
basically s's new book that 800 page
book The reason it's called the crown of
knives is that uh they come back to cut
you what you do to other people comes
back to cut you so I think um and
personally I've I have a lot of Peace
about it now but it wasn't easy the
first few years were very difficult
because it was so uh unjust
and I thought it wasn't
fair but actually karma is the ultimate
fairness okay you you get exactly what
you do you know and so you know a
Buddhist cannot uh complain you just
have to shut up and stop doing it you
know and and but it's emotionally it's
it tears you apart you know it's it's
really hard you know so but like you've
been trying to help people and then and
then it just people attacking you and
then it means you didn't help people
enough
actually so you know as far as their
karma or something like that I think you
can make some honest attempts to correct
them and and helpful and kind
suggestions
like you know that's not nice or you're
going to hurt yourself or something like
that but they don't listen
so I I think you
can you can tell people you know that's
that hurts my feelings and and it's not
true uh but I don't think you should go
farther than that I don't I don't think
there's not there's not they're not
going to stop just because of the
normally so then I I I look ahead at my
life I see how many days I have left on
this this world and I do not want to
spend them thinking about those guys so
I I'm like uh
yeah so I I just like I go on strike you
know emotional on strike you know like I
refuse to think about you and I just wna
I want to use my time for something more
beautiful than arguing with you so I I I
very very
uh strict with my mind I don't allow
myself to waste time CU I don't have
time and I I don't want to spend it like
that I don't want to get in the Cesspool
with somebody and Slug It Out you know I
want to
fly somewhere so okay all right uh